Are you having trouble understanding
your indemnification clause in a
contract? Then you've come to the right
place. I assume that you're not just
watching this for fun, but you have
searched indignification. Most people
get their review of the concept of
indignification in a contract completely
wrong. So, I'll explain it to you.
You're in the right place. My name is
Sarah Sharp. I'm a deal attorney who
helps people buy and sell businesses
every single day. And I'm the founder of
dealacademy.org, where you can learn how
to become the expert in all of the
pieces of the puzzle that go into buying
or selling a business. So check it out.
Indemnification as a concept, it is the
amount that a party has to pay to
another party for certain breaches of
representations, warranties, contract,
covenants, things like that. So that
probably didn't help you much because
it's a little bit of word salad when
there's not anything that is attached to
it. So indignification at a very very
high level can mean something really
different in each application. So every
little piece of the puzzle that makes up
an indemnification clause can be you
know one of 50 different things. And
because of that if you have a whole
bunch of different ingredients to the
indignification cake, right? Then you
change all those ingredients, it can
look very very different. So, one
indemnification clause might say the
seller, you know, is going to pay the
buyer back if uh there's a breach of
representation in the contract and those
representations may elsewhere in the
contract say they survived for like 12
months. That's a pretty limited result,
right? That's just okay. Well, if you
you're kind of agreeing that I have a
breach of contract claim against you and
that you'll pay for it for a brief
period of time. In a different context,
you might have an indemnification clause
that says the seller or buyer are going
to pay each other for anything that
happens, you know, on their side of the
court. So, sellers on the hook for stuff
prior to closing, buyers on the hook for
stuff closing and after, they're going
to pay each other back. And that will
include not just their own breaches of
contract or representations or
covenants, but also third party claims.
And so, that has a completely different
look in application to to things than
the first one. So, the little
ingredients that go into making the
indemnification clause are very
important and they're not boilerplate.
Don't fall into the trap of you get this
kind of rhythmic reading of a contract
and especially when it's filled with
stuff that you don't understand and you
just kind of move on thinking that it
must always say that way. Like, it
doesn't. They're they're very unique.
The scope of what people are agreeing to
pay each other back for is different
from contract to contract. It should be.
The amount of time you're on the hook is
different from contract to contract, but
there's a lot of similarities, right?
Like a lot of times you'll have a cap
and that's what this is about is
indemnification caps. So that's a
maximum amount that either person is on
the hook for it's like a contractual
limit on the amount that a party must
pay to the other party in the
indictification clause. So if that is
triggered then you know that you know
worst case scenar scenario you're not
going to be paying a billion dollars for
something. You're going to have a
limitation to it. They're super
important for just, you know, risk
protectiveness from the seller's
perspective. So, if you're a seller of a
business, when I represent a seller, I
care about almost only two things.
Getting them paid and limiting their
liability. It's much more complex when
you're representing the buyer, you have
a ton more stuff that you care about.
From a seller's perspective, you can be
pretty a twoch single-mindedness about,
you know, making sure you get paid and
limit your liability. So on a go forward
basis, you're going to want a cap that's
pretty low on your indemnification
obligations. And on the buyer side,
they're going to want a cap that's
pretty high. So you can see the tension
that is present, right? So let me
explain to you what I normally see in
the market and how this is resolved in
the sub5 million business acquisition
group. First, check out letter of intent
course at dealacademy.org. We talk a lot
more about end notification in a lot
more detail because I'm so crazy that I
do think you should address this in your
letter of intent. Okay. So, what should
the cat be? If you Google this, you get
the wrong answer. If you open AI it, you
get the wrong answer still. Even though
I'm trying to train the AI. So, there
are some dealter term studies. A dealter
term study is just a like a hyper
analysis of a bunch of deals that have
taken place. And it's very rare for
somebody to be well situated to do such
a a deal term study because for instance
like really big law firms I just saw a
report and the biggest deal M&A firms in
the nation do like 30 deals a year. So I
personally do around 50 because mine are
smaller. So I have pretty robust sample
size. Other people who are like vendors
for instance SRS Aquam puts out a deal
term study. They do escrow and kind of
shareholder type services. So they have
an insight into lots of different deals
as just a vendor outsider. So they have
a deal term study that I constantly get
referred to me in support of you know
just like a variety of opinions. And
some people will say okay in this big
deal term study indemification caps are
like 10% of the purchase price. That is
true. I have seen the dealter term
studies. They do say that that is so
low. So low as to be meaningless in the
context of a small transaction. So, I
have dug in on these deal term studies
and they don't even distinguish a deal
size below $25 million. So, if you have
a $1 million deal and you're trying to
adopt the terms of a deal term study
that doesn't even distinguish between$25
million and $1 million in purchase
price, you're going to overdo it and
you're going to negotiate for really
weird positions. One of the reasons that
indignification cap at the midm market,
meaning 20 million and up, 20 million to
about 200 million, is treated
differently, is because at that level,
it makes sense to bring in reps and
warranties insurance. So, a lot of deals
will be done with a third party who's
just floating around to suck up some of
that liability and risk. That does not
usually make sense at my level, sub$5
million in purchase price. Although, you
know, maybe hit me up if you want to
start a product to sell to people to
have that. It's called RWI insurance for
the smaller transactions. I think that'd
be lovely. But usually that's not
available. So, you have just two parties
instead of three aortioning risk between
themselves. So, 10% I would probably not
want to move forward with in a $5
million or below transaction. But I do
think it's reasonable to start thinking
about the cash received at closing as a
limitation on some liability in that
indomnification clause. So that's
probably as low as I would get.
Somewhere between the cash received at
closing and the overall purchase price
seems to be a reasonable risk
aortionment in small deals because it's
reasonable for the seller to say I don't
want to have to be out of pocket by
virtue of selling my business. That's
too far. You know, if you pay me a
million dollars for my business and then
I get sued, I need to know that I'm not
going to be paying, you know, out of
pocket more money than I even made for
the whole transaction to deal with these
individ claims. That can be appropriate.
But that's all assuming that you have a
deal where the parties are pretty
similarly situated and there isn't some
big weird outlier claim like an ongoing
data breach or something that parties
are anxious about. If that's the case,
you know, you might have no cap or you
might have a really super duper high
cap. And in any event, if you have an
indemnification clause and you then have
a cap on the indemnification, you know,
responsibility of let's say anywhere
between the cash at closing to the
purchase price of the whole deal, great.
You still need to make sure that you
exclude from that cap breaches that are
result of fraud and intentional or gross
misconduct and that kind of thing.
because it doesn't make sense to let
somebody just completely have the
ability to intentionally screw you over
and have negotiated a cap on those
damages. You can imagine the
antithetical to fair outcomes that could
result from that. So, indeification
caps, they're not as complex as it
sounds, but you're also not going to get
good intel out there because there's
just not a granularity in people's
research of how these deals are done.
The vast majority either have no cap at
all or the cap is somewhere between the
closing the amount received at closing
and let's say 2x the purchase price.
That is what I see in the market and
what I other attorneys that are
similarly situated see as well. If you
found this valuable, please like and
subscribe. Check out dealacademy.org.
Share it with your friends and fame.